BRUNO LACERDA

Senior Researcher in Robotics https://ori.ox.ac.uk/~bruno bruno@robots.ox.ac.uk

ABOUT ME

I am currently a Senior Researcher in Robotics at the Goal-Oriented Long-Lived Systems (GOALS) Lab, Oxford Robotics Institute, University of Oxford. My research focuses on the intersection of decision making under uncertainty, formal methods and mobile robotics. In particular, I am interested on the use of a combination of techniques from learning, planning and model checking to synthesise intelligent, robust and verifiable behaviour, both for single and for multi-robot systems.

Research Interests

- · Sequential Decision Making under Uncertainty
- · Probabilistic Model Checking
- · Planning for Robotics
- · Multi-Robot Coordination
- · Service Robotics
- · Discrete Event Systems

EDUCATION

Instituto Superior Técnico, Lisbon, Portugal

· PhD in Electrical and Computer Engineering

2009 - 2013

Thesis: Supervision of Discrete Event Systems Based on Temporal Logic Specifications

Advisor: Pedro U. Lima

· MSc in Mathematics and Applications

2002 - 2007

Thesis: Linear-Time Temporal Logic Control of Discrete Event Systems

Advisors: Pedro U. Lima, Francisco M. Dionísio

· BSc in Applied Mathematics and Computation

2002 - 2007

RESEARCH POSITIONS

Oxford Robotics Institute, University of Oxford, Oxford, UK

· Senior Researcher in Robotics

September 2018 – Present

· Postdoctoral Research Assistant in Robotics

September 2017 – September 2018

University of Birmingham, Birmingham, UK

April 2013 – September 2017

· Postdoctoral Research Fellow in Intelligent Robotics

Örebro University, Örebro, Sweden

September 2008 - December 2008

· Research Intern

Instituto Superior Técnico, Lisbon, Portugal

March 2008 - August 2008

· Research Intern

CONTRIBUTION TO PROJECTS

University of Oxford

- · Offshore Robotics for Certification of Assets (ORCA). UK Research and Innovation
- · Robotics and Artificial Intelligence for Nuclear (RAIN). UK Research and Innovation

University of Birmingham

- · Spatio-Temporal Representations and Activities for Cognitive Control in Long-Term Scenarios (STRANDS). EU-FP7
- · Novel Dynamic Vehicle Scheduling and Path Planning Algorithms for Mobile Robotic and AGV Warehouse Order Picking. TSB Smart Award
- · Learning the Structure and Dynamics of Human Environments to Support Intelligent Mobile Robot Behaviour. EPSRC First Grant

TEACHING

University of Oxford

· Lecturer: Probabilistic Model Checking Shared lecturing duties with Marta Kwiatkowska Michaelmas Term 2018

University of Birmingham

Invited Lectures: Robot Programming Semester 2 2015/2016, 2016/2017
 Delivered two lectures each year on multi-robot coordination
 Lecturer: Intelligent Robotics Semester 1 2014/2015

Shared lecturing duties with Chris Burbridge and Lars Kunze

Invited Research Lecture: Intelligent Robotics

Demonstrator: Foundations of Computer Science

Semester 1 2013/2014

Semester 1 2013/2014

STUDENT SUPERVISION

University of Oxford

PhD Co-Supervisor (w/ Nick Hawes): Charlie Street
 Topic: AI for Multi-Robot Systems PhD Co-Supervisor (w/ Nick Hawes): Marc Rigter
 Topic: Shared Autonomy with Formal Guarantees PhD Co-Supervisor (w/ Nick Hawes): Michael Painter
 Topic: Multi-Objective Mission Planning 4th Year Project Supervisor: Han Zhou
 Topic: Auctioning for Multi-Robot Coordination September 2018 – Ongoing
 September 2018 – Ongoing
 October 2018 – Ongoing

University of Birmingham

· PhD Co-Supervisor (w/ David Parker and Nick Hawes): Fatma Faruq February 2017 – Ongoing Topic: Simultaneous Task Allocation and Planning under Uncertainty

· PhD Co-Supervisor (w/ Nick Hawes): Lenka Mudrova June 2014 – September 2017 Topic: Task Scheduling and Merging in Space and Time

· MSc Summer Project (w/ Jeremy Wyatt): Milan Tomy June 2017 – September 2017 Topic: Battery Scheduling in Autonomous Mobile Robots

· BSc Final Year Project (w/ Nick Hawes): Joseph Shaw October 2016 – April 2017 Topic: Auctioning for Multi-Robot Coordination

· MSc Summer Project (w/ Nick Hawes): Pedro Elias June 2015 – September 2015 Topic: Multi-agent Path Finding

· MSc Summer Project (w/ Nick Hawes): Eliot Dixon June 2014 – September 2014

Topic: MDP Models for Mobile Service Robots

• MSc Summer Project (w/ Nick Hawes): Ken Poyner June 2013 – September 2013

Topic: Autonomous Navigation Cost Estimation In Mobile Robots

RESEARCH VISITS

Delft University of Technology, Delft, The Netherlands

May 2016 – July 2016

· Host: Matthijs Spaan

University of California, Los Angeles, CA, USA

September 2011 – December 2011

· Host: Paulo Tabuada

University Carlos III de Madrid, Madrid, Spain

March 2010 - June 2010

· Host: Miguel A. Salichs

AWARDED FUNDING

LEaDing Fellows, a Marie Curie COFUND Programme

July 2018

- 2 Year Fellowship
- · Research Proposal: "Cooperative Multi-Robot Transportation Systems with Guaranteed Quality of Service"
- · Declined opportunity and stayed at University of Oxford

LES & EPS PERCAT Career Development Competition, University of Birmingham March 2016

· Travel support for research visit to TU Delft

Ramsay Research Travel Fund, School of Computer Science, University of Birmingham March 2016

· Subsistence support for research visit to TU Delft

Fundação para a Ciência e Tecnologia, Portugal

· Funding for PhD student research visit to UCLA

April 2011

· Funding for PhD student research visit to UC3M

November 2009

INVITED TALKS

- · Workshop on Formal Methods in AI, University of Naples Federico II, Naples, Italy February 2017
- · Computer Science Department Seminar Series, University of Liverpool, UK

March 2017

· Robolog Workshop, IRISA, Rennes, France

June 2017

· Full-day Tutorial at 4th Lucia PhD School on AI and Robotics, Lisbon, Portugal September 2017

SERVICE

University of Oxford

· Organiser of the Oxford Robotics Research Group Seminars (w/ Siddharth Narayanaswamy)

May 2018 – Present

 \cdot Engineering Research Associate at Pembroke College

August 2018 – Present

· Participated in robot demo and Pembroke College Open Day

June 2018

· Lead robot demo at Blenheim Palace, Woodstock, Oxfordshire

January 2019

University of Birmingham

· Participated in several robot demos at various locations, e.g., London's Museum of Natural History, Birmingham's Think Tank, School of Computer Science and University of Birmingham's Open Days 2014-2018

Reviewing

- · Artificial Intelligence (AIJ)
- · IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control (TACON)
- · IEEE Robotics & Automation Magazine (RAM)
- · Discrete Event Dynamic Systems (DEDS)
- · IEEE Transactions on Automation Science and Engineering (T-ASE)
- · IEEE Control Systems Letters (L-CSS)
- · IEEE Transactions on Systems, Man, and Cybernetics (SMC)
- · IEEE Transactions on Intelligent Systems (IS)
- · International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI) 2017 2019
- · AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI) 2018, 2019
- \cdot International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems (AAMAS) 2014, 2016 2019
- · International Conference on Automated Planning and Scheduling (ICAPS) 2016 2019
- · European Conference of Artificial Intelligence (ECAI) 2016, 2018
- \cdot International Conference on Tools and Algorithms for the Construction and Analysis of Systems (TACAS) 2017
- · International Symposium on Distributed Autonomous Robotic Systems (DARS) 2014
- · IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA) 2015, 2018
- · IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS) 2015 2018
- · IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC) 2018
- · American Control Conference (ACC) 2016, 2018
- · IEEE International Conference on Automation Science and Engineering (CASE) 2015, 2016
- AAAI Spring Symposium on Integrating Representation, Reasoning, Learning, and Execution for Goal Directed Autonomy - 2018
- Introspective Methods for Reliable Autonomy Workshop @ IROS 2017 Workshop on Autonomous Mobile Service Robots @ IJCAI 2016
- · AI for Long-term Autonomy Workshop @ ICRA 2016
- · Workshop on Autonomous Robots and Multirobot Systems @ AAMAS 2016 Workshop on Artificial Intelligence and Robotics @ AAAI 2014, 2016
- · AAAI Robotics Fellowships 2015, 2016

INDUSTRY POSITIONS

Everis, Consulting, IT, Outsourcing & Professional Services, Lisbon, Portugal

September 2007 - February 2008

· Junior Consultant

Mercer Human Resource Consulting, Lisbon, Portugal

April 206 – September 2006

· Part-time Collaborator

PUBLICATIONS

Under Review

- [1] Bruno Lacerda, Fatma Faruq, David Parker, and Nick Hawes. "Probabilistic planning with formal performance guarantees for mobile service robots". In: *International Journal of Robotics Research (IJRR)* (Conditionally Accepted).
- [2] Masoumeh Mansouri, Bruno Lacerda, Nick Hawes, and Federico Pecora. "Multi-Robot Planning Under Uncertain Travel Times and Safety Constraints". In: *Proc. of the 28th Int. Joint Conf. on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI)*. Submitted.

[3] Marc Rigter, Bruno Lacerda, and Nick Hawes. "Learning to Act from Demonstrations with Minimal Human Input". In: *Proc. of the 2019 IEEE/RSJ Int. Conf. on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)*. Submitted.

Journal Publications

- [4] Nick Hawes, Christopher Burbridge, Ferdian Jovan, Lars Kunze, Bruno Lacerda, Lenka Mudrova, Jay Young, Jeremy Wyatt, Denise Hebesberger, Tobias Kortner, Rares Ambrus, Nils Bore, John Folkesson, Patric Jensfelt, Lucas Beyer, Alexander Hermans, Bastian Leibe, Aitor Aldoma, Thomas Faulhammer, Michael Zillich, Markus Vincze, Eris Chinellato, Muhannad Al-Omari, Paul Duckworth, Yiannis Gatsoulis, David C. Hogg, Anthony G. Cohn, Christian Dondrup, Jaime P. Fentanes, Tomas Krajnik, Joao M. Santos, Tom Duckett, and Marc Hanheide. "The STRANDS Project: Long-Term Autonomy in Everyday Environments". In: *IEEE Robotics Automation Magazine* 24.3 (2017).
- [5] Bruno Lacerda and Pedro U. Lima. "On the Notion of Uncontrollable Marking in Supervisory Control of Petri Nets". In: *IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control* 59.11 (2014).
- [6] Bruno Lacerda and Pedro U. Lima. "Linear-Time Temporal Logic Control of Discrete Event Models of Cooperative Robots". In: *Journal of Physical Agents* 2.1 (2008).

Conference Publications

- [7] Fatma Faruq, Bruno Lacerda, Nick Hawes, and David Parker. "Simultaneous Task Allocation and Planning Under Uncertainty". In: *Proc. of the 2018 IEEE/RSJ Int. Conf. on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)*. Madrid, Spain, 2018.
- [8] Bruno Lacerda, David Parker, and Nick Hawes. "Multi-Objective Policy Generation for Mobile Robots Under Probabilistic Time-Bounded Guarantees". In: *Proc. of the 27th Int. Conf on Automated Planning and Scheduling (ICAPS)*. Pittsburgh, PA, USA, 2017.
- [9] Lenka Mudrová, Bruno Lacerda, and Nick Hawes. "Partial Order Temporal Plan Merging for Mobile Robot Tasks". In: *Proc. of the 22nd European Conf. on Artificial Intelligence (ECAI)*. The Hague, Netherlands, 2016.
- [10] Lenka Mudrová, Bruno Lacerda, and Nick Hawes. "An Integrated Control Framework for Long-Term Autonomy in Mobile Service Robots". In: *Proc. of the 7th European Conf. on Mobile Robotics (ECMR)*. Lincoln, United Kingdom, 2015.
- [11] Bruno Lacerda, David Parker, and Nick Hawes. "Optimal Policy Generation for Partially Satisfiable Co-Safe LTL Specifications". In: *Proc. of the 24th Int. Joint Conf. on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI)*. Buenos Aires, Argentina, 2015.
- [12] Jaime Pulido Fentanes, Bruno Lacerda, Tomáš Krajník, Nick Hawes, and Marc Hanheide. "Now or later? Predicting and maximising success of navigation actions from long-term experience". In: *Proc. of the 2015 IEEE Int. Conf. on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)*. Seattle, WA, USA, 2015.
- [13] Bruno Lacerda, David Parker, and Nick Hawes. "Optimal and dynamic planning for Markov decision processes with co-safe LTL specifications". In: *Proc. of the 2014 IEEE/RSJ Int. Conf. on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)*. Chicago, IL, USA, 2014.
- [14] Bruno Lacerda and Pedro U. Lima. "LTL-Based Decentralized Supervisory Control of Multi-Robot Tasks Modelled as Petri Nets". In: *Proc. of the 2011 IEEE/RSJ Int. Conf. on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)*. San Francisco, CA, USA, 2011.
- [15] Bruno Lacerda and Pedro U. Lima. "Designing Petri Net Supervisors from LTL Specifications". In: *Proc. of Robotics: Science and Systems VII (RSS)*. Los Angeles, CA, USA, 2011.
- [16] Bruno Lacerda and Pedro U. Lima. "Designing Petri Net Supervisors for Multi-Agent Systems from LTL Specifications (Extended Abstract)". In: *Proc. of the 10th Int. Conf. on Autonomous Agents and Multi-Agent Systems (AAMAS)*. Taipei, Taiwan, 2011.
- [17] Bruno Lacerda, Pedro U. Lima, Javi Gorostiza, and Miguel A. Salichs. "Petri Net Based Supervisory Control of a Social Robot with LTL Specifications". In: *Proc. of the 11th Int. Conf. on Mobile Robots and Competitions*. Lisbon, Portugal, 2011.

[18] Bruno Lacerda and Pedro U. Lima. "Petri Nets as an Analysis Tool For Data Flow in Wireless Sensor Networks". In: *Proc. of the 1st Portuguese Conference on Wireless Sensor Networks* (CNRS). Coimbra, Portugal, 2011.

Workshop Publications

- [19] Bruno Lacerda, David Parker, and Nick Hawes. "Policy Generation with Probabilistic Guarantees for Long-term Autonomy of a Mobile Robot". In: *Proc. of the Int. Workshop on the Verification and Validation of Autonomous Systems (VaVAS)*. Oxford, United Kingdom, 2018.
- [20] Bruno Lacerda, David Parker, and Nick Hawes. "Nested Value Iteration for Partially Satisfiable Co-Safe LTL Specifications (Extended Abstract)". In: AAAI Fall Symposium on Sequential Decision Making for Intelligent Agents (SDMIA). Arlington, Virginia, USA, 2015.
- [21] Bruno Lacerda, David Parker, and Nick Hawes. "Optimal Motion Planning for Markov Decision Processes with Co-Safe Linear Temporal Logic Specifications". In: *Proc. of th 31st Workshop of the UK Planning & Scheduling Special Interest Group (PlanSIG)*. Edinburgh, Scotland, UK, 2014.
- [22] Bruno Lacerda and Pedro U. Lima. "LTL Plan Specification for Robotic Tasks Modelled as Finite State Automata". In: *Proc. of Workshop ADAPT at AAMAS '09 Agent Design: Advancing from Practice to Theory.* Budapest, Hungary, 2009.